Good morning. So today's דף daf is ט"ו tet vav 15 and
it's going to be a
doozy. So we pick up
with the מעשה מרכבה Maaseh Merkavah discussions that were being had with
רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai and רבי אלעזר בן
ערך Rabbi Elazar ben Arach and then similarly with רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua and this רבי יוסי הכהן. Rabbi Yossi HaKohen. And we pick
up and they had the that and רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai said he had this vision of them by הר
סיני Har Sinai actually like reclining which is fascinating, the concept of
like ויאכלו וישתו Vayocheilu Vayishtu that we have at הר סיני, Har
Sinai, the eating, and then being called up the mountain and eventually
to this castle and being the third group in the presence of
God. So the גמרא Gemara says איני, Eini, is this true? והתניא,
Veha Tanya, it's by the asterisk about ten lines down in the
wide
lines. רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yossi b'Rabbi Yehuda Omer, שלשה
הרצאות הן. Shlosha Hartza'ot hein. An הרצאה Hartza'ah in modern Hebrew is
a lecture, right? Anyway, but this is שלשה הרצאות Shlosha Hartza'ot basically
means thank you like a clearly a disposition on מעשה מרכבה.
Maaseh Merkavah. So there are three of these things, there's three sets
of these. Let's take a look. רבי יהושע הרצה דברים לפני רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי, Rabbi Yehoshua hirtza devarim lifnei Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai,
רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua laid out the issues מעשה מרכבה Maaseh Merkavah
in front of רבי יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai. רבי
עקיבא הרצה לפני רבי יהושע Rabbi Akiva hirtza lifnei Rabbi Yehoshua and
then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva also learned מעשה מרכבה. Maaseh Merkavah. And
again, remember yesterday when רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva wanted to דרש darash
a פסוק pasuk about two
chairs and who was in the second throne, they said go to
מגדל עז. Migdal Oz. But here we have that רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva is expounding on מעשה מרכבה, Maaseh Merkavah, so clearly whatever
his ability was in the area of אגדתא, Aggadeta, he certainly the
sense that he was a mystic and involved in this is clear.
So anyway, so רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua discussed מעשה בראשית, Maaseh Breishit,
מעשה מרכבה Maaseh Merkavah in front of רבי יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai.
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in front of רבי יהושע, Rabbi Yehoshua, he
was a student of רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua of רבי יהושע Rabbi
Yehoshua and חנניה בן חכינאי הרצה לפני רבי עקיבא Chananya ben Chachinai
hirtza lifnei Rabbi Akiva and חנניה בן חכינאי Chananya ben Chachinai presented
discussed מעשה מרכבה Maaseh Merkavah in the presence of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi
Akiva. So it's all רב-תלמיד Rav-Talmid relationships. So it went down four
generations. ואילו רבי אלעזר בן ערך לא קחשיב, Ve-ilu Rabbi Elazar ben
Arach lo kachashiv, and it doesn't mention רבי אלעזר בן ערך Rabbi
Elazar ben Arach expounding on it before רבי יוחנן בן זכאי. Rabbi
Yochanan ben Zakkai. So how does that fit with this previous story?
So the גמרא Gemara says דארצי וארצו קמיה קחשיב. D'artzi ve-artzu kamei
kachashiv. No, the whole point of this story was to create this
chain,
רב-תלמיד רב-תלמיד, Rav-Talmid Rav-Talmid, of discussing מעשה מרכבה. Maaseh Merkavah. So somebody
who presented and it was presented to him, that is mentioned in
this list. דארצי ולא ארצו קמיה, D'artzi velo artzu kamei, by רבי
אלעזר בן ערך, Rabbi Elazar ben Arach, he might have presented מעשה
מרכבה Maaseh Merkavah to רבי יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai
but he never had a תלמיד talmid that picked up on this
stuff and presented it to him. So you don't have that chain
of tradition. So therefore לא קחשיב, lo kachashiv, that's not in the
list. And it should just be mentioned briefly about רבי אלעזר בן
ערך Rabbi Elazar ben Arach that on the one hand רבי אלעזר
בן ערך Rabbi Elazar ben Arach is מעין המתגבר Ma'ayan Hamitgaber which
we say in פרקי אבות, Pirkei Avot, right? And that's why רבי
יוחנן בן זכאי Rabbi Yochanan ben Zakkai was astounded that he was
able to figure all of this out about מעשה מרכבה. Maaseh Merkavah.
On the other hand, we have very little material in the תלמוד
Talmud or anywhere based from רבי אלעזר בן ערך. Rabbi Elazar ben
Arach. And the reason, or it's connected to a story of רבי
אלעזר בן ערך, Rabbi Elazar ben Arach, that he went to, I
forgot the city, but a particular city where there were not a
lot of תלמידי חכמים talmidei chachamim and I think he was, the
story was that he was like attracted by the good bathhouses and
whatever. And he figured, he's such a huge תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
and he's able anyway to be so self-sufficient that the
other sages and students will follow after him. Did we have that
a few days ago? I don't think so. But anyway, and the
story was of course that they did not follow after him and
and that's based and brought in discussions like הוי גולה למקום תורה,
Hevei goleh limkom Torah, you have to go after it, it won't
come after you and so on. And in the end he basically
the well sort of dried up and he actually lost a lot
of his learning and we have like almost no traditions based on
him. So that's obviously consistent with this idea here that he was
not, he did not have a student that followed him that then
continued in that tradition here relating to מעשה מרכבה. Maaseh Merkavah. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says והא חנניה בן חכינאי דלא ארצו
קמיה? Veha Chananya ben Chachinai d'lo artzu kamei? But the last guy
in the list, חנניה בן חכינאי, Chananya ben Chachinai, he presented in
front of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva but nobody presented to him. So
the גמרא Gemara says וקחשיב? vekachashiv? He's counted.
So how's that different than רבי אלעזר בן ערך? Rabbi Elazar ben
Arach? So the גמרא Gemara says no, דארצי מיהא קמיה מאן דארצי.
D'artzi miya kamei man d'artzi.
No, at least he presented to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva who presented
to רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. Obviously that allows us to have that
chain of A presented to B presented to
C etc., sort of chain רב-תלמיד רב-תלמיד, Rav-Talmid Rav-Talmid, which you don't
have by רבי אלעזר בן ערך. Rabbi Elazar ben Arach. Okay. Okay,
so that's the end of those rabbis who discussed מעשה מרכבה. Ma'aseh
Merkavah. Now we get to a very famous גמרא. Gemara. תנו רבנן,
Tanu Rabbanan, a rabbi taught: ארבעה נכנסו בפרדס, arba'ah nichnesu b'Pardes, four
entered into the garden, to the פרדס, Pardes, right, which is all
clearly understood as some type of a heavenly ascent,
you know, either mystical study or going up to heaven. רבנו חננאל
Rabbeinu Chananel brings down
a discussion of this in the ערוך Aruch that basically talks about
it as a vision. Actually, but let's read and then I want
to read the piece from רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel because it's quite
fascinating. So who are the four that entered in? ואלו הן, v'eilu
hein, these are: בן עזאי Ben Azzai ובן זומא, u'Ben Zoma, אחר,
Acher, אחר Acher is אלישע בן אבויה, Elisha ben Avuyah, ורבי עקיבא.
v'Rabbi Akiva. Those are the four. אמר להם רבי עקיבא, Amar lahem
Rabbi Akiva, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said to them: כשאתם מגיעים
אצל אבני שיש טהור, keshe'atem magi'im eitzel avnei shayish tahor, when you
get to the stones of pure marble, which will be up in
their up in this garden, up in this, you know, heavenly ascent,
so and that'll presumably be close to the presence of God, אל
תאמרו מים מים, al tomru mayim mayim, don't say, oh, water, water,
it'll look like water, משום שנאמר דובר שקרים לא יכון לנגד עיני,
mishum shene'emar doveir shekarim lo yikon leneged einai, the one who speaks
falsehood will never will not be established in my presence, and it's
not water. Very fascinating of all the things to worry about. בן
עזאי הציץ ומת. Ben Azzai heitzitz vamet.
When they got up there בן עזאי Ben Azzai peered and died.
So did he peer at these stones or other you know it
might alternatively be understood, the מהרש"א Maharsha understands it, I'll mention רמב"ם
Rambam in a minute, like no, he actually tried to peer maybe
through the wall or he tried to peer to actually to have
a direct vision of God that was not one that one should
be having, and he died as a result. עליו הכתוב אומר alav
hakatuv omeir and
regarding him the verse says: יקר בעיני השם המותה לחסידיו, yakar be'einei
Hashem hamavta l'chasidav,
dear in the eyes of God of God is death to his
righteous ones. So apparently it's making a point of framing him as
חסידיו, chasidav, not necessarily you know not sort of holding him at
fault for this.
The מהרש"א Maharsha at least tries to explain, I'll mention רמב"ם Rambam
in a minute, that you know that this was like his soul
directly you know had communion with God and therefore the body died
because he reached this tremendously high level. Again, it does seem it's
a little interesting ambivalent, הציץ ומת, heitzitz vamet, like if you peer
and you die, it sounds like you did something wrong, but then
trying to underscore that not to hold him, you know, at fault
or to not certainly not to blame him. בן זומא הציץ ונפגע.
Ben Zoma heitzitz v'nifga. בן זומא Ben Zoma on the other hand
peered and he was injured as a result. Doesn't exactly say what
that injury was although it's commonly understood to be well I don't
commonly, certainly after the aftermath of As a Driven Leaf, understood
understood to be, you know, to be that he went a little
crazy. So
עליו הכתוב אומר, alav hakatuv omeir, regarding him it says: דבש מצאת
אכול דייך, dvash matzata echol dayeka, had you found honey then eat
your fill eat what is is sufficient, פן תשבענו והקאתו, pen tisba'enu
vehikeito,
lest you sate yourself or you eat too much honey and then
you will spit it out because it's too much of it will
be disgusting. So he went beyond what he could handle and as
a result he actually was injured, whatever that injury was. So again,
it does seem to be making the difference. They both peered, one
was maybe able to handle it but somehow died as a result,
which again does not sound great unless you read the מהרש"א's Maharsha
way, but the other clearly there's some sense of censure or some
sense of having done something wrong and he was left injured as
a result. אחר, Acher, אלישע בן אבויה, Elisha ben Avuyah, קיצץ בנטיעות.
kitzetz b'netiyot. He cut the young shoots. You're going into a garden.
The worst thing to do in a garden is to to cut
the young sprouts, right? Those are the things that are going to
be growing the best and there you are you he was very
destructive. רבי עקיבא יצא בשלום, Rabbi Akiva yatza b'shalom, רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva was the only one that exited in peace without being injured
as a result. Okay, now before we get to the aftermath of
this, I want to just read a very fascinating רבנו חננאל. Rabbeinu
Chananel. If you take a look at רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel here
he says the following: he says,
פירוש, peirush, you see where there's like a little asterisk and a
parentheses in רבנו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel at the beginning of a line
about twenty lines down? So on the right-hand margin here, so it's
one line over that, he says פירוש, peirush, כינוהו פרדס, kinnu'uhu Pardes,
they referred to this thing as פרדס, Pardes, מעין גן עדן, mei'ein
Gan Eden, שהוא גנוזה לצדיקים, shehu genuzah l'tzaddikim, it's like גן עדן
Gan Eden which is hidden for the righteous, כך אותו מקום הוא
מקום בערבות, kach oto makom hu makom ba'Aravot, remember ערבות Aravot which
is that one of those high heavens up the one closest to
God, שהנשמות של צדיקים צרורות בו, she'haneshamot shel tzaddikim tzrurot bo, that's
where the righteous souls are, which we mentioned in the earlier גמרא,
Gemara, ומפורש בהיכלות, u'meforash b'Heichalot, and it's explained in the היכלות Heichalot
literature, which is the earliest like of mystical literature, שהיו החכמים הראויים
למידה הזו, she'hayu hachachamim har'u'im l'middah hazu, the sages that were able
to achieve this level, מתפללים, mitpalelim, they would pray, ומנקים עצמם מכל
דבר טומאה, u'menakim atzmam mikol davar tumah, and they would cleanse themselves
from all impure things, וצמים, v'tzamim, and they would fast,
ומטבילים, u'matpilim, and they would go to the מקוה, mikvah,
ומטהרים, u'mitaharim, and they would purify themselves, והיו משתמשים בשמות, v'hayu mishtamshim
b'shemot, they would use the divine names, וצופים. v'tzofim. צופים בהיכלות vtzofim
beheichalos and they would look at the היכלות heichalos which are like
the chambers up in heaven, right, they would get a vision of
those chambers, ורואים איך משמרות המלאכים ועמדם vroim eich mishmaros hamalachim vaamdam
and this is obviously patterned after the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, they
saw how the how the you know the different what's it called
not troops but guards,
watches of the angels are watching the היכל, heichal, you know, the
divine
temple. והיכל אחרי היכל vheichal acharei heichal and how there's one temple,
you know, or one chamber inside you know after the next one.
ולפנים מהיכל vlifnim meheichal ולפנים
מהיכל vlifnim meheichal and what is inside of the of the chamber.
וציווה אותם רבי עקיבא כשאתם מגיעים להביט באובנתא דליבא vtziva osam Rabbi
Akiva keshatem magiim lehabit beuvnusa dliba when you now he makes a
point when you got when you are when you are getting ready
to look באובנתא דליבא beuvnusa dliba Schachter would translate that as in
your mind's eye. Okay, so you're not actually seeing something physical. This
is a mystical vision that you are having. You are preparing yourself
for this you know out-of-body mystical experience and you are having this
type of a vision and you're seeing like in your heart, you're
seeing in your mind's eye when you are prepared to see that
אצל
אבני שיש טהור etzel avnei shayish tahor when you get to the
pure marble stones אל תאמרו מים מים al tomru mayim mayim שאין
שם מים כל עיקר she'ein sham mayim kol ikar אלא דמות בעולם
נראית. ela dmus baolam nires. It's only some type of a vision.
האומר מים נדחף haomer mayim nidchaf or נהדף nehdaf and somebody and
somebody that says water somehow is pushed out שנמצא משקר shenimtza meshaker
בלשון הזה מפורש בהיכלות רבתי. balashon hazeh meforash beHeichalos Rabbasi. And this
is how it's spelled out in היכלות רבתי, Heichalos Rabbasi, which is
one of the works of the היכלות Heichalos literatures. Okay, מפני ששומרי
ההיכל mipnei sheshomrei haheichal this is what's explained there, those who guard
the divine chamber, פתח
שיש pesach shayish מטילין ומשליכין אלף אלפי גלי מים. matilin umashlichin elef
alfei galei mayim. So there's a opening of of marble
and somehow poured out of it these tremendous waves of water. ואין
שם אפילו טיפה אחת. ve'ein sham afilu tipah achas. And even though
it looks like there are these waves of water coming out, there's
really not even a drop of water. Okay. ואמר רבי עקיבא ve'amar
Rabbi Akiva נראה כמי שיש בו גלי מים nireh kemi sheyesh bo
galei mayim it looks like there are these waves of water ואין
בה אפילו טיפה אחת ve'ein bah afilu tipah achas אלא אוויר זיו
אבני שיש טהור ela avir ziv avnei shayish tahor it's just the
glowing of these marble stones שהן קלוט בהיכל shehen kalut baheichal שהיה
זיו פניהם דומה למים shehaya ziv pneihem domeh lemayim that that somehow
is included in the in the divine chambers that the appearance looks
like water. והאומר מים הללו מה טיבן vehaomer mayim halalu mah tivan
and anybody says what's this water about נהדף. nehdaf. Okay, ואינם עולים
בשמים ve'einam olim bashamayim now he again underscores they did not really
go up to heaven אלא צופים ורואים באובנתא דליבא ela tzofim vroim
beuvnusa dliba they saw it in their mind's eye. כאדם הרואה ומביט
מתוך אספקלריה שאינה מאירה. ke'adam haroeh umehabit mitoch aspaklaria she'eina me'ira. Like
somebody who sees through a cloudy lens, okay, that's another phrase about
seeing through a cloudy lens. All the נביאים neviim saw through a
cloudy lens, משה Moshe was the only one who saw through a
clear lens. And now just to finish this, he says ובן עזאי
הציץ uBen Azzai hetzitz ובן עזאי uBen Azzai peered, כלומר הוסיף להזכיר
בשמות klomar hosif lehazkir bshemos he add he said additional divine names
to go even to a higher mystical state, okay, כדי להביט באספקלריה
מאירה kdei lehabit be'aspaklaria me'ira because he wanted to see in the
uncloudy lens. ומת umes and he died as a result. בן זומא
הציץ ונפגע Ben Zoma hetzitz venifga כלומר נטרפה דעתו. klomar nitrefah da'ato.
So you see, this was before Milton Steinberg, so he went crazy.
אחר קיצץ בנטיעות Acher kitzetz banetiyos so it says and he called
it קיצץ בנטיעות kitzetz banetiyos because what do you do to be
destructive in a garden? You cut down the various נטיעות netiyos and
then he goes on. So anyway, I just thought that that was
quite fascinating, right, associating this with the whole היכלות Heichalos which is
some of the earliest mystical practices that we have. You know when
people talk about mysticism, they tend to talk about it as like
a, you know they think about the זוהר Zohar and they think
about like describing things but they forget this whole theurgic element of
the mysticism which is creating these mystical states and getting these visions
and that is very much, you know, the היכלות Heichalos literature pretty
much describes what was the practice of those mystics and identifies that
type of mystical practice of getting these visions and saying divine names
and seeing visions of the castle and so on as what was
being described here with this proper entering the פרדס. Pardes. Yes yes.
Is the מים mayim here as a way מים mayim is just
a metaphor for תורה? Torah? I don't know, I really don't know
what this whole thing is with the water. But why do you
say that? In the גמרא Gemara yes מים mayim is very often
a metaphor for for תורה. Torah. What?
Why? Because it just רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is talking about מים?
mayim? I mean, I don't see the theme sort of like, you
know, resonating else, you know, here elsewhere in that story. The מים
mayim thing I really don't have a good handle on.
Not to say that שקר. sheker. Oh, שקר בתורה. sheker baTorah. Maybe.
I'm saying what it is. Right. Right. Could be, could be. So
you know, I'm I'm at sea
here on the top, yes so.
I'm interested in the saying of the repetition of the divine names.
Not repeating, saying different ones, get you to a higher level. So
it's it's a pretty like sacred, reserved for special moments type of
thing. Right.
Oh that's anticipated in order to, it's in order to effect the
spiritual experience. You get yourself ready through fasting and going to the
מקוה mikvah and meditating and so on and then when you're ready
look some people used to do this whole thing about being משפיע
המלאכים, mashpia hamalachim, right? It's like, you know, trying to manipulate the
angels through saying different types of things. It's not exactly I, again,
I'm not I don't really know this stuff. But somehow the power
of the name allows a person, it effects the vision, allows a
person to achieve this mystical state. I'm equating it with like how
we're kind of reserved in our use of God's names. Right. Totally.
Of course. So there's like it seems like a very... Well, it
wasn't, it wasn't prolific. This was, you know, this was only for
the most, you know, elite and, you know, prepared for it and
only at the, you know, after they'd gone through this whole thing.
But yes, there was the use of divine names. There's no question.
That goes back in many other forms also, in the use of
amulets and other types of things, you know, the Rabbis obviously were
not in favor of that. But every now and then you do
have the Rabbis talking about using a divine name and, you know,
that definitely but again, not that it was prolific. Yeah. What? Like
the
שם המפורש? Shem HaMeforash? Like using the names? Right. Oh yeah, אמת?
emet? Okay, yeah. Okay, so just for one more second about this
because again this is so power you know this is such a
dominant thing. So as a slightly different version of this we have
Rambam's approach, which is which is that he says that we're talking
about, you know, about the study of theology. And he talks about
how if we try to use our physical faculties
like we try to look at something and look deeper and deeper
if we're not able to if our eye isn't ready we'll strain
our eye and hurt our eye. So he says,
okay, something similar can happen to you with regard to intellectual apprehensions.
For if you stay your progress because of a dubious point, if
you do not deceive yourself into believing that there is a demonstration
with regard to matters that have not been demonstrated, if you do
not hasten to reject and categorically to pronounce false any assertions whose
contradictions have not been demonstrated, if finally you do not aspire to
apprehend that which you are unable to apprehend, so if you know
the limits of your intellect and you don't try to understand things
that you're not able to, you will achieve human perfection in the
rank of Rabbi Akiva, who entered in peace and went out in
peace, נכנס בשלום ויצא בשלום. nichnas beshalom veyatza beshalom. We don't have
the, but that will come later. When engaged in the theoretical study
of metaphysical matters. If, on the other hand, you aspire to apprehend
things that are beyond your apprehension,
etc. etc., you will have joined אלישע אחר. Elisha Acher. That is,
you will not only not be perfect, but you will be most
deficient among the deficient and it shall fall out that you will
be overcome by imaginings and by an inclination towards things defective, evil,
and wicked. This results from the intellect being preoccupied and its light
being extinguished. In a similar way, various species of
delusive imaginings etc. etc. Okay. And then it goes with the eating
of the honey, da da da da, illicit foods like honey. According
to nature, honey if eaten to excess upsets the stomach and causes
vomiting. Accordingly, Scripture says that in spite of its sublimity, greatness, and
as perfection, the nature of the apprehension in question if not made
to stop at its proper limit may be perverted into a defect.
And he goes on and on. So anyway, Rambam reads this very
much about about the intellect's ability to understand and the problem about
wrecking your intellect beyond its ability and very much in a rationalist
sense here about the study of metaphysics, but metaphysics for him is
not mystical stuff, it's basically like theology. And so the Rambam reads
all of this very much in terms of the study of theology.
Okay, I would say that that's not פשט. pshat. Okay, now the
גמרא Gemara continues. Let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara. So that
was the story of what happened to those four and now we're
going to get, we're going to focus on on the various ones.
So there's not too much to say about Ben Azzai who died,
so we're going to talk now about Ben Zoma. שאלו את בן
זומא. Sha'alu et Ben Zoma. So they asked Ben Zoma: מהו לסרסי
כלבא? Ma hu l’sarshei kalba? Can you, can you castrate a dog?
Because it's something that would never even be in the category of
a קרבן. korban. So is that allowed? You know, the concerns around
those things tend to be קרבנות korbanos related concerns. אמר להם, Amar
lahem, he said to them: ובארצכם לא תעשו. U’v’artzachem lo ta’asu. כל
שבארצכם לא תעשו. Kol shebe’artzachem lo ta’asu. It's
in the verse about castrated animals, don't bring them as sacrifices, it
says "do not do that in your land." So he says anything
in your land, any animal, not even animals that would be sacrifices,
which creates major halakhic problems for people that have pets, about, you
know, anyway getting them spayed and neutered. לא תעשו. Lo ta'asu. Okay.
שאלו את בן זומא. Sha’alu et Ben Zoma. Now what this has
to do with anything I don't know, let's keep on going, but
they asked Ben Zoma: בתולה שעיברה מהו לכהן גדול? Besulah she'ibra mahu
l'kohen gadol?
If a virgin becomes pregnant, what is her story for a כהן
גדול? kohen gadol? A כהן גדול kohen gadol has to marry a
virgin. So the basic question is, do we believe that somebody could
become, a woman could become pregnant and still be a virgin? מי
חיישינן לדישמואל? Mi chashinan l'deShmuel?
Are we concerned for Shmuel? דאמר שמואל: D'amar Shmuel: יכול אני לבעול
כמה בעילות בלא דם. yakhol ani liv’ol kamma be’ilot belo dam. This
is a whole discussion in כתובות. Ketubot. Shmuel said, "I can have
sex with a virgin many times and without it actually breaking the
hymen." So maybe this woman has her hymen intact but she still
actually has had sex and therefore halakhically would not be a virgin
and would and therefore would not be allowed to marry a כהן
גדול. kohen gadol. או דלמא דשמואל לא שכיח? O dilma deShmuel lo
shchiach? Or do we say Shmuel, you know, that that is uncommon?
And therefore if it's uncommon...
Therefore she never had sex. So if she never had sex, how'd
she get pregnant? So אמר להו דשמואל לא שכיח. amar lehu deShmuel
lo shchiach. שמואל's Shmuel thing is not common. So if she's pregnant,
it's unlikely that she...
I'm sorry, so if so if so if there's not a reasonable
explanation that her has her hymen intact and is pregnant, a reasonable
explanation is not that she had sex because that would be unlikely
for her to have had sex and to be pregnant. So that's
not the explanation of how she's pregnant and her hymen is intact.
So what's the explanation? So the explanation is וחישינן שמא באמבטי עיברה.
vechashinan shema be'ambati ibra. She got pregnant in a bathhouse. She went
into a bath that a man had been in before and had
ejaculated into and that's how she got pregnant. That's a more reasonable
explanation than that she had sex without it rupturing the hymen. So
the גמרא Gemara says והאמר שמואל, ve'ha'amar Shmuel,
how can you say that? But doesn't שמואל Shmuel also say כל
שכבת זרע שאינו יורה כחץ אינו מזרעת, kol shichvat zera she'eino yoreh
kechetz eino mazra'at,
any semen that does not come out as an arrow, you know,
does not sort of you know come out with force, it cannot
will not inseminate? So you know, how can how'd she get inseminated
in terms of being in a bathhouse? So it says מעיקרא נמי
יורה כחץ הוה. me'ikara nami yoreh kechetz hava. No, it doesn't mean
it has to enter her body when it's sort of coming out
that way. It just means it has to exit the man coming
out that way. So that's how it got into the water in
the bath and but that was still semen of the quality that
could impregnate, that could that could cause conception and then when it
entered her body it caused her to conceive. So while this seems
you know
completely fantastical and you know I'm not going to try to defend
the the assertion the scientific assertions here, but it does become a
very important גמרא Gemara for discussion of artificial insemination. You know and
so and there you know although I don't know the interesting facts
about is it ever able to would it ever be able to
extract a semen without it being ejaculated and that would I don't
you know I can't I don't imagine that would affect its potency.
So but anyway bracketing that issue about יורה כחץ yoreh kechetz and
so on, we do know it is possible to you know for
semen coming out of a man's body in one stage and being
put in the woman's body in another stage. Whether that can happen
by being in the water of a bathhouse you know is a
different question, will it get into where it needs to get and
so on. But anyway then becomes interesting questions around the discussions nowadays
of A, the permissibility of it and B, the question about paternity
and so on, which again you don't have that discussed here, but
that becomes like the model and it gets discussed elsewhere as we
quoted the other day the work of Ben Sira. There's a מדרש
Midrash that that's sort of about how Ben Sira was born and
so on. So anyway that becomes interesting in terms of that. Now
what the heck this is doing here, first of all let's point
out that this whole issue about quoting שמואל Shmuel and quoting him
twice is the גמרא's Gemara inserting because שמואל's Shmuel after you know
בן זומא. Ben Zoma.
So so the actual original text just said they said מהו לכהן
גדול mahu leKohen Gadol and he responded
probably the response was אמר להו חיישינן שמא באמבטי עיברה. amar lehu
chaishinan shema be'ambati ibra. Right,
now maybe it became in a bathhouse. All the שמואל Shmuel insertions
are are not there but nevertheless it's still the same basic question
and answer. What this is doing here I honestly don't know. It
could be because we're about to see another discussion with בן זומא
Ben Zoma about mystical matters where he seems to be off the
דרך. derech. So what this might be doing here is just to
establish before we get to that that however this impacted his mind
and his intellect, he was still able to have normal types of
halachic discourse. The problem was was when he tried to deal with
mystical matters as we'll see in the next story. That's one possibility.
The other obvious thing, and of course I might be projecting here,
the obvious thing that occurs to a person is that well we
do know stories of a virgin who became pregnant. So was
is that trying to suggest somehow that he is you know that
that part of his being נפגע nifga was being influenced by you
know by Christian thought? I really have no idea if that's maybe
being suggested. I so have no idea how it connects to the
story about the dog and castrating the dog. So I really it's
hard to know what exactly this story is doing here. Yes. I
read an article about בן זומא, Ben Zoma, the texts of בן
זומא Ben Zoma relating to tying into Christianity. Okay oh really? Other
other other texts that show that his possible
influence by Christianity or? Ben Sira as being kind of sort of
doing more of a Jewish Christian proto-Gospel.
Interesting.
Interesting interesting. So maybe that is what this... so then you would
have to try to figure out if there's some hidden message in
the whole dog and castrating thing also that might be associated with
that. We just the I just like was curious halachically about a
בעולה be'ulah and a בתולה, betulah, is בתולה betulah breaking the hymen?
No, so that's the point. If we're if we assume that the
answer the explanation is שמואל, Shmuel, then she's not a בתולה. betulah.
But is there so the point is how'd she become pregnant? The
most logical explanation is she had sex and the hymen didn't break.
Then she wouldn't be a בתולה, betulah, then she'd be אסור לכהן
גדול. asur leKohen Gadol. Maybe there's another explanation. So she says, no,
she couldn't have had sex, so there's got to be another explanation.
The explanation is this שמא באמבטי. shema be-ambati. But again, notice going
to this possibility of the Christianity idea that his response is, don't
try, if you see a virgin that's pregnant, don't try to explain
it in a way that says that she had sex. No, she's
really a virgin and she's pregnant, right? That's the end of his
answer, right? So he says באמבטי, be-ambati, but the end is he's
saying she still is really she really is a virgin she's never
had sex. So again thinking that this has some issues with Christianity
I would say is not so farfetched. But you have to figure
out the dog story. Okay, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. Now our rabbis
taught. מעשה ברבי יהושע בן חנניה, Maaseh b'Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya, story
with רבי יהושע בן חנניה Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya שהיה עומד על
גב מעלה בהר הבית, she-hayah omed al gav maalah be-Har ha-Bayit, he
was on a one of an elevation on the Temple Mount, וראהו,
v'ra'ahu, which is itself very fascinating, right aren't they all טמאי, tamei,
what are people doing on the Temple Mount? וראהו v'ra'ahu בן זומא
Ben Zoma and בן זומא Ben Zoma saw him, ולא עמד מלפניו,
v'lo amad milfanav, and he didn't stand up in his presence. בן
זומא Ben Zoma did not stand up and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
was at a higher level, well you know, was like a רבי
rebbe to בן זומא. Ben Zoma. He was בן זומא Ben Zoma
was the next generation.
So, אמר לו, amar lo, so רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said to
him, מאין ולאין בן זומא, me-ayin u-le-ayin Ben Zoma, where are you
coming from and where are you going בן זומא? Ben Zoma? Your
head is so up in the clouds, right? You didn't even see
me. Of course, one wonders if that's also meant to evoke מאין
באת ולאן אתה הולך. me-ayin bata u-le-an attah holekh. Okay, anyway, but
what's going on בן זומא? Ben Zoma? אמר לו, amar lo, he
said to him, צופה הייתי בין מים העליונים למים התחתונים, tzofeh hayiti
bein mayim ha-elyonim la-mayim ha-tachtonim, I was peering between the
supernal waters and the lower waters, ואין בין זה לזה אלא שלוש
אצבעות, v'ein bein zeh la-zeh ela shalosh etzba'ot, and there's only three
fingerbreadths that separate them, בלבד, bilvad, ושנאמר, v'shenemar, ורוח אלוהים מרחפת על
פני המים, v'ruach Elohim merachefet al pnei ha-mayim, the spirit of God
hovered over the waters, כיונה שמרחפת על בניה, k'yonah she-merachefet al baneha,
like a dove that hovers over its children, ואינה נוגעת, v'eina noga'at,
doesn't touch. So but it's a little bit above, it's a three
fingers above. So this רוח אלוהים ruach Elohim somehow represents the supernal
waters, remember water, here's the water theme again, water, water, so somehow
represents the supernal waters and it's only three טפחים tefachim above the
lower waters. אמר להן רבי יהושע לתלמידיו, Amar lahen Rabbi Yehoshua l'talmidav,
so רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said to his students, right, עדיין בן
זומא מבחוץ, adayin Ben Zoma mibachutz, בן זומא Ben Zoma is still
on the outside. So he's still not well, is presumably, or he's
outside of the, you know, he or what he's saying is maybe
even quasi-heretical, you know, he's not, but he's obviously not really getting
it in terms of the mystical vision. So again, one way of
reading it is it was okay the halakhic discussion tried to but
then his head you'll bump into him sometimes if you get him
in the בית מדרש Beit Midrash he might give you a rational
halakhic answer, but you bump into him in the street his head
is completely in the clouds, he's not aware of his surroundings, and
he's thinking weird thoughts in terms of mysticism, things that are off
base. So that's עדיין בן זומא מבחוץ. adayin Ben Zoma mibachutz. Yes.
But I associate רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua with rational halakhic answers and
not esoterica. Right, but רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua you remember is one
of the people on the previous דף daf that was being עוסק
במעשה מרכבה osek be-Maaseh Merkavah too. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Now we're gonna have why that's really the end of
the story, but you know, that's where the original story ends. If
you see the shift here, this insertion here of Aramaic, so where
the גמרא Gemara inserts. So the real story just ends with עדיין
בן זומא בחוץ, adayin Ben Zoma bachutz, which is like a powerful
end to a story. But anyway now the גמרא Gemara analyzes it
some more. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. מכדי, mikhdi, let's
take a look. ורוח אלוהים מרחפת על פני המים, v'ruach Elohim merachefet
al pnei ha-mayim, אימת הוי, eimat havi, when was that? ביום הראשון,
beyom ha-rishon, that was on day one. So how could בן זומא
Ben Zoma be bringing evidence from what things were on day one?
Things changed after day one. הבדלה, havdalah, ביום שני הוא דהוי, beyom
sheni hu d'havi, the separation of the upper and lower waters was
on the second day. So דכתיב, dikhtiv, ויהי מבדיל בין מים למים.
v'yehi mavdil bein mayim la-mayim. Okay,
וכמה, v'kamma, so that's why that's so that's what the גמרא Gemara
says is that's why it's clear that בן זומא's Ben Zoma off
base. So now how much is the actual separation of the upper
and lower waters? וכמה, v'kamma, אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav
Acha bar Yaakov, כמלא נימא. k'mlo nima. No, it's not three three
fingers, it's just like a hair's breadth. ורבנן אמרי, v'rabbanan amri, כגודא
דגמלא, k'guda d'gamla, like the planks of a bridge. You know the
wood planks they're right next to each other, there's only the tiny
little space you know that's between them because you can't actually you
know make things you know merge. So that tiny little space that
exists between the planks of a bridge. מר זוטרא ואיתימא רב אסי,
Mar Zutra v'iteima Rav Assi, אמר, amar, כתרי גלימי דפרסי אהדדי, k'trei
glimei d'parsei ahadadei, like two pieces of garment that were sewn you
know right up against one another. So there or that were spread
next to each other. So again you know there's only the tiniest
separation between them. ואמרי לה, v'amrei lah, כתרי כסי דסחיפי אהדדי, k'trei
kassi d'shachifei ahadadei, and some say that it's two cups that were
like turned you know one on top of the other. And again
there's only like the slightest separation between them. So I really understand
everything that this symbolizes, but I'm not allowed to tell you. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara says,
all right, so that's the story of the בן זומא. Ben Zoma.
Again, but you know again that later part was added later in
the גמרא Gemara to just show oh he got it wrong. But
of course if you read it that way, oh he got it
wrong, it wasn't three three fingers, it was like a hair's breadth.
So obviously you could say there's profound you know mystical significance in
that too. Also maybe it's more significantly wrong that he was looking
at the first day of creation and clearly the info you know
the right understanding was based on the second day of creation. But
you know but all of a sudden it becomes more. more detailed
and technical once the story just ends with like, oh my god,
he's still
nuts, עדיין בחוץ, adayin bachutz, this like a more sort of powerful
type of an ending. And maybe nuts is not the right word,
but whatever. His head is still not in the right place. Okay.
What happened in the פרדס pardes story? Yeah, so there's now post-פרדס.
pardes. So there's nothing to say about בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, he's
dead. So now we told first the stories of בן זומא, Ben
Zoma, first these halakhic discussions and then, but his head is in
the clouds and he can't answer, give reasonable answers in terms of,
you know, the sort of mystical things he's thinking about. And now
we're going to turn to אלישע בן אבויה, Elisha ben Abuyah, and
then we're going to turn to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. So we're
going through each one of them. Yes, I saw a translation of
this story where it's like just his words in English like, what
are you doing? And he's like, oh, I was just staring at
the above and I saw how the space between the high water,
the low water is like three fingers, like a dove. Yes, like
a dove flutter. And he's like,
oh, בן זומא Ben Zoma is still outside. Right. Right, off about
him. Crazy. In another world. Got it. Right. Today, they would be
asking you what you were smoking. Right. Okay. Alright, so yes. Alright,
so now
אחר. Acher. אחר קיצץ בנטיעות. Acher kotzetz bintiyot. אחר's Acher cut down
the young shoots. עליו הכתוב אומר alav hakasuv omer regarding him the
verse says, אל תתן את פיך לחטיא את בשרך. al titten es
picha lachati es besarecha. Do not allow your mouth to bring, you
know, sin or whatever, guilt to yourself, meaning it was something that
he said wrong or did wrong that ultimately brought him down. Let's
see what that is. מאי היא, mai hi, what is that? חזא
מיטטרון דאיתיהיבא
ליה רשותא. chaza Metatron de'isyevlei reshutha. Now again, I'll just point out
to you that this we're now reading Aramaic. So this is now
not part of that original tannaitic version of what happened. This is
a later גמרא Gemara description, and by the way, there's a whole
ירושלמי Yerushalmi that has similar material, but also different material, some of
it quoted in תוספות Tosafos if we get a chance I'll read
some of that. Okay, so he saw מיטטרון Metatron who was like
the head angel up in heaven. דאיתיהיבא ליה רשותא, de'isyevlei reshutha, and
that he was,
מיטטרון Metatron was given permission למיתב lemisav to sit, למכתב זכוותא דישראל,
lemichtav zachvatha deYisrael,
to write the merits of the Jewish people. אמר, amar, so he
saw this מיטטרון Metatron sitting and you know, מיטטרון, Metatron, it wasn't
just like a head angel, there's like stuff which is somehow maybe
even a manifestation of God or some type. Anyway, he's very high
up. Okay, anyway, so he was sitting and he was writing down
the merits of Israel. אמר, amar, he says, so בן זומא Ben
Zoma says, גמירנא, gemirna, we have a tradition דלמעלה לא הוי לא
ישיבה ולא תחרות ולא עורף ולא עיפוי. de'lemala lo havai lo yeshiva
velo tachrut velo oref velo ipuy. There's no sitting up above in
heaven in the presence of God and there's no competition, ולא עורף,
velo oref, there's no back of the necks because they have faces
on all four sides, ולא עיפוי, velo ipuy,
and there's not wearying. So how could this be that he's sitting?
Now of course what's interesting is we're not questioning the tradition. It's
not like, oh my tradition must be wrong. No, there's a real
problem here, he's sitting and it's not supposed to happen in the
presence of God. שמא חס ושלום שתי רשויות הן. shema chas veshalom
dvei reshuyos hen. Maybe there are two ultimate powers, right? So if
somebody can sit in the presence of God, they're a competing power
against God. So that was his heretical thought. אפקוהו למיטטרון, apku lei
leMetatron, so then they, so then up in heaven they kicked out
מיטטרון, Metatron, which is so fascinating, right? Like the idea about thinking
about you know, Christian ideas and Satan being rejected, you know, kicked
out of heaven. So here מיטטרון Metatron is being kicked out of
wherever he
was in that inner chamber. ומחיוהו שיתין פולסי דנורא, umachyu lei shittin
pulsi denura,
and they lashed him with sixty, you know, tongues of flame. Now
what is immediately said in רבינו חננאל Rabbeinu Chananel and elsewhere is
like, it wasn't that מיטטרון Metatron did anything wrong. How could he
be punished? He's an angel, whatever. Anyway, you know, he was given
permission, but that was done explicitly in order to demonstrate to אחר
Acher that God was God, that there was nobody that was competing
against God's power. So they immediately saw מיטטרון Metatron punished. But again,
one does think of some of the Christian mythologies around this issue.
Okay. אמר ליה מאי טעמא כי חזיתיה, amar lei mai taama ki
chazisa, so they said to מיטטרון, Metatron, whoever the they is, what's
the reason when you saw him, when you saw אחר, Acher, לא
קמת מקמיה? lo kamta mikamei? So you didn't stand up in his
presence, not that you should stand to respect אחר, Acher, but that
he should not have had these heretical thoughts. Okay,
so we don't know the answer, but they gave him a hard
time again, מיטטרון, Metatron, for not standing up, but again as is
explained, it's not like he did anything wrong, but it was just
to demonstrate God, that God, you know, God as the supreme power.
So, איתיהיבא ליה רשותא, isyevlei reshutha, now permission was given to apparently
מיטטרון Metatron again, למימחא זכוותא דאחר, lemimcha zachvatha deAcher, to erase, again
very appropriate for being two days before ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, so
there was writing the merits of Israel, but now that אחר Acher
has committed heresy, he was given permission to erase the merits of
אחר. Acher. יצתה בת קול ואמרה. yazta bas kol ve'amra. Okay, now
that's the Aramaic insertion. Okay, in the original text again, all it's,
it did not give any detail to how he was heretical and
what he saw. It just says אחר קיצץ בנטיעות Acher kotzetz bintiyot
and quotes the verse. Okay, so this whole story with מיטטרון Metatron
as the explanation is the גמרא's Gemara insertion into the original story.
Okay, the real next line of the original source was, אחר Acher
committed heresy and then... And then יצתה בת קול bat kol ואמרה
*yatzta bas kol ve'amra*, a heavenly voice came out and said, שובו
בנים שובבים *Shuvu banim shovavim*, return wayward children, חוץ מאחר *chutz me'Acher*,
except for אחר Acher *Acher*. Okay, so basically he had no chance
of returning. אמר Amar, *Amar*, so now אחר Acher *Acher* said, הואיל
ואיטריד *ho'il ve'itred*, notice again now the shift to Aramaic, so now
we're back into a גמרא'ס *Gemara's* elaboration, הואיל ואיטריד ההוא גברא *ho'il
ve'itred hahu gavra*, since this person has been completely like rejected מההוא
עלמא *me'hahu alma*, you know, has been you know distanced from this
world,
from that world, excuse me, from the world to come, ליפוק ליה
בהאי עלמא *leipuk leih behai alma*, I might as well get some
benefit from this world, okay, so he became a hedonist. נפק אחר
Acher לתרבות רעה *Nafak Acher letarbut ra'ah*. So אחר Acher *Acher* went
out to bad behavior. תרבות *Tarbut* is interesting, right, we say תרבות
*tarbut* is like culture nowadays, but you know probably also means that
he like embraced the Greek type of a way of life and
that culture and became you know hedonistic and so on. Okay, so
that he, so that's what he did. He now went down the
wrong path. He might as well enjoy this world if I'm not
getting the world to come. נפק *Nafak*, he went down. אשכח זונה
*Ashkach zonah*, he found a prostitute. תבעה *Tava*, he you know demanded
sex. אמרה ליה *Amra leh*, she said to him, ולאו אלישע בן
אבויה Elisha ben Abuyah את *vela'av Elisha ben Avuya at*? I don't
understand, aren't you this great Rabbi? עקר פוגלא ממשרא *Akar pugla mimashera*,
it was שבת *Shabbos*, so he went and he took a turnip
out of the out of the bed, you know out of the
where it was planted, on שבת *Shabbos*, ויהיב לה *veyahaiv lah*, and
gave it to her. אמרה אחר Acher הוא *Amra Acher hu*, no,
that's someone else. Okay, so that's obviously אחר Acher. *Acher*. Okay, to
show, look, I don't keep שבת *Shabbos*, it's like nothing, it's nothing
for him to break שבת *Shabbos*. Okay, now, ושאיל אחר Acher *veshaul
Acher*, now that again, that whole story about the, the story about
מטטרון *Metatron*, the story about the prostitute, was a גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
insertion. The original story was much more sparse, just he went, he
went off the דרך derech. *derech*, you know he committed heresy and
the heavenly voice said everybody can return except אחר Acher. *Acher*. Now,
לאחר *le'Acher*, now we're back though to the original Hebrew source.
Okay, where are we? Okay, שאל אחר Acher את רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir *sha'al Acher et Rabbi Meir* אחר שיצא לתרבות רעה Acher sheyatza
l'tarbus ra *achar sheyatzah letarbut ra'ah*. So אחר Acher. *Acher* asked רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rabbi Meir* after he went off the דרך derech.
*derech*, מהר *maher*? אמרי ליה *Amrei lei*, מאי דכתיב mai d'kesiv, *mai
dichtsiv*, what's meant by the verse, גם את זה לעומת זה עשה
האלוהים *gam et zeh lumat zeh asah ha'Elokim*? Notice by the way
the parallel in the original version. Right? בן זומא *Ben Zoma* is
נפגע *nifga* and we have stories of halachic discussions with בן זומא
*Ben Zoma*. אחר Acher, *Acher* is יצא לתרבות רעה yatza l'tarbus ra
*yatzah letarbut ra'ah* and then we also have discussions of like rabbinic
types of discussions with him that immediately follow. Okay, so what's meant
by the verse, גם את זה לעומת זה עשה האלוהים *gam et
zeh lumat zeh asah ha'Elokim*? This opposite this God has made. אמרי
ליה *Amrei lo*, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* said to
him, you know, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* was like a
lower generation, like a student of אחר Acher *Acher*, right? He was
the next generation. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* said to
him, אמרי ליה *amrei lo*, where am I? Okay, כל מה שברא
הקדוש ברוך הוא ברא כנגדו *kol mah shebara hakadosh baruch hu bara
kenegdo*.
Everything God has created, he's created its opposite. ברא הרים ברא גבעות
*Bara harim bara geva'ot*. He made mountains, he made valleys. ברא ימים
ברא נהרות *Bara yamim bara
naharot*. And he made, you know, oceans, he made rivers.
אמר ליה *Amar lo*, he said to him, רבי עקיבא רבך לא
אמר כך Rabbi Akiva rabecha lo amar kach, *Rabbi Akiva rabcha lo
amar kach*. That's not how רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva *Rabbi Akiva* your
רבי rebbi *Rebbe* explains it. אלא *Ella*, ברא צדיקים ברא רשעים *bara
tzaddikim bara resha'im*. ברא גן עדן Gan Eden, ברא גיהנום Gehennom. *Bara
Gan Eden bara Gehennom*. And much more deep sense of opposites, right?
Anyway, how is an ocean and a river an opposite? So number
one, the sense of opposite is more clear in this version, and
also it's about, you know, spiritual issues. Okay? ברא גן עדן Gan
Eden. ברא גיהנום Gehennom, *Bara Gan Eden bara Gehennom*. כל אחד ואחד
יש לו שני חלקים *Kol echad ve'echad yesh lo shenei chalakim*. Everybody
has two portions. אחד בגן עדן *Echad be-Gan Eden*, one portion waiting
for you in גן עדן Gan Eden, *Gan Eden*, ואחד בגיהנום *ve'echad
be-Gehennom*, and one portion waiting for you in גיהנום Gehennom, *Gehennom*. זכה
צדיק *Zachah tzaddik*, if a righteous person merits, נטל חלקו וחלק חברו
בגן עדן *natal chelko ve-chelek chavero be-Gan Eden*, he gets his portion
and the sort of the abandoned portions of people who are
רשעים *resha'im*, so they have sort of forfeited their portions in גן
עדן Gan Eden? *Gan Eden*, so that's that's taken by the צדיק
*tzaddik*. So he gets double. בגן עדן *Be-Gan Eden*. נתחייב רשע rasha
*Nit-chayev rasha*, the wicked person becomes is found guilty, נטל חלקו וחלק
חברו בגיהנום *natal chelko ve-chelek chavero be-Gehennom*. He gets his portion that's
been designated for him plus the portions that have been forfeited in
גיהנום Gehennom. *Gehennom* from the צדיקים *tzaddikim*. So basically everybody gets paid
that double what they're deserving in this scheme. Okay, but it sort
of preserves the divine economy, I guess, of זה לעומת זה *zeh
lumat zeh*, you know, but somehow everything has a you know has
a has a parallel and a balance. And it's interesting because it
suggests that the other rabbis not following, not necessarily following his path.
Ah, so he was like warning off of the consequences of going...
yeah he was saying don't, yeah don't follow me if you stick
with with you know your path you'll get double. You'll get double,
right. Okay. Interesting. The
point about the world being pretty evenly split between
צדיקים *tzaddikim* and רשעים *resha'im* so there's not a... there's not a...
there's not some extra stuff left. And yet that's a good point
too and the זה לעומת זה *zeh lumat zeh*, it's not just
there are צדיקים *tzaddikim* there are רשעים *resha'im*, for this whole economy
to work out there's got to be an equal number of each.
That's a good point. Okay. Yeah. The way בן עזאי went in
was...
Right, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was his colleague, right, and רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was the one that was נכנס בשלום, nichnas b'shalom,
right, exactly. And one does wonder if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said
this, you know, one wonders if רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva made this
point to אחר Acher. after אחר Acher was יצא לתרבות רעה and
sort of and then אחר Acher is sort of using this to
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, and essentially as a way of communicating like
look at how I've been rejected, you know, from the my rabbinic
colleagues. This is what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, said. Okay.
Okay. אמר רב משארשיא, Amar Rav Mesharshya, מאי קרא? mai kra?
What's the verse that supports this? גבי צדיקים כתיב, gabi tzaddikim kesiv,
לכם בארצה משנה ירשו, lachem b'artza mishneh yirashu, in their land you
will inherit double. גבי רשעים כתיב gabi reshaim kesiv and by the
wicked it says ומשנה שברון שברם, umishneh shivaron shivram,
and double of a of a destruction of a of a breaking
is their, you know, is their downfall. Okay. שלח אחר לרבי מאיר
Shalach Acher l'Rabbi Meir now, another thing אחר sent to רבי מאיר,
Rabbi Meir אחר שיצא לתרבות רעה
after אחר went off the דרך. מאי דכתיב, what's meant by the
verse, לא יערכנה זהב וזכוכית, lo yaarchenah zahav uzechuchis,
it will not be compared to it gold and and glass,
first glass is cheap, but in the ancient world glass was very
expensive, ותמורתה כלי פז, utemurasah kli paz,
and its exchange with, you know, vessels of gold. אמר לו, amar
lo, so רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said to him, אלו דברי תורה,
eilu divrei Torah, these are the words of תורה, Torah, שקשים לקנותם
ככלי זהב ופז, shekashim liknosam kichlei zahav v'paz, they
are as difficult to acquire as gold and פז paz another word
for gold, ונוחין לאבדן ככלי זכוכית, v'nochin l'avdan kichlei zechuchis, and they
are so easy to lose, תורה, Torah,
like if you break a break a glass, it's, you know, so
it's very easy to to lose. I still remember my first year
in ישיבה yeshiva in Israel, I was in this small ישיבה yeshiva
and like somehow there was like a week or two going by
that there was a lot of, remember those those tea glasses that
they had in Israel, those tall thin little tea glasses? Anyway, so
everybody was drinking tea by their place, and somehow like a week
went by and like three people accidentally knocked over their glasses and
we had like a breaking of these glasses in the ישיבה. yeshiva.
So somebody put up this line from the גמרא Gemara up on
the ישיבה, yeshiva, says נוחין לשברם ככלי זכוכית nochin lishavram kichlei zechuchis
because he thought that it was a סימן siman about the how
we were doing in our learning. Anyway, so okay. אמר לו, amar
lo, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva, רבך לא אמר כך, that's not how
רבי עקיבא, your rebbe explains this verse. אלא מה? ella ma? כלי
זהב וכלי זכוכית אף על פי שנשברו
יש להם תקנה, kli zahav u-kli zechuchis af al pi shenishberu yesh
lahem takanah, the same way gold vessels and and glass vessels, even
if they break they can be fixed, right, you can resmelt them
and you can remelt the glass, אף תלמיד חכם אף על פי
שסרח יש לו תקנה. af talmid chacham af al pi shesarach yesh
lo takanah.
So there is obvious relevance to that. A תלמיד חכם talmid chacham
even if he has become spoiled, right, he can still be fixed.
There's still hope. Now again, I don't really even know how to
deal with these two different statements of רבי עקיבא, right, one is
saying the רשע rasha... is going to get paid double, which it
seems to be very much of a castigating, you know, and kicking
him out type of a statement, and here the statement like יש
לו תקנה, yesh lo takanah, but I guess held in combination, you
know, it's saying look, if you stay in your way, you're going
to get a double punishment, but it's not hopeless, יש תקנה yesh
takanah and if you go back and become righteous, you'll actually get
a double reward. So sort of held together, it's a little like,
you know, pushing with the left hand and pulling back with the
right or somehow trying to both, you know, sort of scare him
but also give him the incentive that you can still do תשובה.
teshuva. Yes. And maybe even the opening phrase, חלק בגן עדן. chelek
b'Gan Eden. Yes. That's like the...
Oh, that's the inspiring thing. Like every single person, including a רשע...
I see. You start with a חלק בגן עדן. chelek b'Gan Eden.
So and you can lose it, you just choose which one you
want. Aha. So you can ultimately reclaim your חלק בגן עדן chelek
b'Gan Eden because it's sort of always there waiting for you. That's
a nice point. Right. So it seems taken together this is sort
of very encouraging. And what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, said was, you
know, was either neutral or discouraging. So anyway, okay. אמר לו, amar
lo,
so then רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, said to him, if that's what
you're saying, אף אתה חוזר בך, af ata chozer becha, so do
תשובה. teshuva. אמר לו, amar lo, so אמר לו amar lo he
said back to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir no, כבר שמעתי מאחורי הפרגוד,
kvar shamati meachorei hapargod, I heard from behind the curtain, whatever that
is, שובו בנים שובבים
חוץ מאחר, shuvu banim shovavim chutz mei-Acher, return wayward children other than
אחר. Okay, now by the way, we're going to find later that,
you know, statements that like he really could have done תשובה teshuva
even though that was the message he was getting, שובו חוץ מאחר,
shuvu chutz mei-Acher, ultimately, okay, you know, but he had to manage
to have the strength and perseverance to say even with that message
he's going to do תשובה, teshuva, you know, and show that, you
know, I'm going to prove that wrong, you know, that was sort
of part of the the the test as it were. But the
other thing to point out here is like again, you know, who
is he hearing the בת קול bat kol from? Is he hearing
it from himself or is he hearing it, you know, from heaven?
You know, and how much is this a story about him just
having decided for himself that he was a lost cause and not
wanting to have been persuaded? I mean, you know this happens sometimes
to people, right? That they basically feel they've given up on themselves,
I'm a lost cause, and people will try to persuade them, no,
come on, you can make things better, and he says no, no,
there's no hope for me. So that's like, you know, you could
read this in a very psychological way and not in this בת
קול way. בת קול *bas kol* way, like, he just believed deeply
that it was not going to make any bit of a difference.
And no matter what anybody said to him, it was, you know,
"Everybody can do תשובה *teshuvah* except me." Yeah, because the basic rabbinic
theology is that anybody can do תשובה *teshuvah*. So, you know, so
that either that this was a divine test or that it was
his own, you know, the messages he was giving himself. Yes. This
prohibition not to despair, but also this mental illness. Right.
Well, that's true too. And then you try so hard to help
somebody and they're right. Right. Right. And they still can't come back.
Right. Right. That's really that's true as well. Yes. This would have
been chronologically after the בת קול *bas kol* was rejected by רבי
יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* and established, so we don't listen to heavenly voices.
Oh, that's about halakhic matters. Okay, anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this. Okay, מעשה באחר שהיה רוכב על הסוס *ma’aseh
b’Acher hayah rocheiv al hasus*, so he was riding on a horse
בשבת *b’Shabbos*, right? ורבי מאיר מהלך אחריו *ve’Rabbi Meir mehalech acharav*, and
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* was following after him ללמוד תורה
Torah מפיו *lilmod Torah mipiv*, to learn תורה Torah. *Torah* from his
mouth. אמר לו *Amar lo*, he said to him, מאיר חזור לאחוריך
*Meir chazor l’achorecha*, Meir you should turn back, שכבר שיערתי בעקבי הסוס
*she’kvar shi’arti b’ikvei hasus*, I've measured with the steps of the horse,
עד כאן תחום שבת *ad kan techum Shabbos*, that we've gotten up
to the שבת *Shabbos* boundary. So here he is violating שבת *Shabbos*
riding a horse, but he says to him, "You better stop now
because you're about to violate שבת *Shabbos*. I don't want my sort
of things to mislead you." אמר ליה *Amar lei*, so רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir. *Rabbi Meir* said to him on a play on words,
אף אתה חזור בך *af atah chazor becha*. So you're telling me
to turn away from the path I'm on, you should turn away
from the path you're on. Come do תשובה *teshuvah*. אמר ליה *Amar
lei*, ולא כבר אמרתי לך *ve’lo kevar amarti lach*, כבר שמעתי מאחורי
הפרגוד *kevar shamati me’achorei hapargod*, שובו בנים שובבים חוץ מאחר *shuvu banim
shovavim chutz me’Acher*? Haven't you haven't I already told you that there's
no hope for me? Everybody can do תשובה *teshuvah* except for אחר
*Acher*. Okay. Now we get to again a גמרא *Gemara* insertion into
this earlier story. תקפיה *Takfei*, so רבי מאיר *Rabbi Meir* wouldn't accept
that answer. He grabbed hold of him. עייליה לבי מדרשא *Ailey l’bei
midrasha*, he shlept him into the בית המדרש *beis hamidrash*. אמר ליה
לינוקא *Amar lei l’yanuka*, he said to a child, פסוק לי פסוקך
*pesok li pesukach*. So this is a famous sort of way of
like looking for סימנים *simanim*, you know, or of like hints to,
you know, to what God is to sort of like, you know,
what's awaiting for a person, or you know, a way to get
communication from heaven is to ask a random child what פסוק *pasuk*
are you learning? And that, you know, it's sort of like people
have heard like the גורל הגר"א *goral HaGra*, like you'd open up
a תנ"ך *Tanakh* and point your finger and whatever wherever your finger
lands that פסוק *pasuk* would somehow be symbol, you know, sort of
be a סימן *siman* of like some message from heaven. So they
did this by taking a random child out of, you know, who
was learning in חדר *cheder* and said what פסוק *pasuk* are you
learning? And he'd say a פסוק *pasuk* and that would be significant
about a message that was being communicated to this person. So he
said, "Tell me what פסוק *pasuk* you're learning." אמר לו *Amar lo*,
אין שלום אמר ה' לרשעים *ein shalom amar Hashem l’resha’im*, "There is
no peace," says God to the wicked. Okay, that's not helpful. עייליה
לבי כנישתא אחריתי *Ailey l’bei knishta achriti*, brought him into another בית
כנסת *beis knesses*. It's quite fascinating. The first one said בית מדרש
Midrash *beis medrash* and this says another בית כנסת *beis knesses*. So
might be some issues here of the text. Anyway, אמר ליה לינוקא
פסוק לי פסוקך *amar lei l’yanuka pesok li pesukach*, he said to
a child, "Tell me your פסוק *pasuk*." אמר לו *Amar lo*, כי
אם תכבסי בנתר ותרבי לך ברית *ki im techabsi baneser ve’tarbi lach
boris*, "If you if you cleanse yourself with, you know, lye and
you have a lot of soap, נכתם עונך לפני *nichtam avoneich lefanai*,
your sin is still stained before Me." Not helpful again. עייליה לבי
כנישתא אחריתי *Ailey l’bei knishta achriti*, another בית כנסת *beis knesses*. אמר
ליה לינוקא *Amar lei l’yanuka*, פסוק לי פסוקך *pesok li pesukach*, "Tell
me your the פסוק *pasuk* you're learning." This is רבי מאיר *Rabbi
Meir* telling it to these children to try to get a good
פסוק *pasuk*. אמר לו *Amar lo*, ואת שדוד מה תעשי *ve’at shadud
u’mah ta’asi*, "And you, you know, who are staying in captivity, what
can you do? כי תלבשי שני כי תעדי עדי זהב *ki tilbishi
shani ki ta’adi adi zahav*, if you dress yourself in scarlet or
wear, you know, golden jewelry, כי תקרעי בפוך עיניך *ki tikre’i bapuch
einayich*, if you put, you know, mascara on your eyes, לשוא תתיפי
*lashav tityafi*, for naught you are trying to make yourself look beautiful,"
and the end of the verse is even worse. Okay, so עייליה
לבי כנישתא אחריתי *Ailey l’bei knishta achriti*, brought him into another בית
כנסת *beis knesses*. עד דעייליה לתליסר בי כנישתא *Ad d’ailey l’tlasar bei
knishta*, he tried thirteen בתי כנסת *batei knesses*. כולהו פסקו ליה כהאי
גוונא *Kulu pasku lei k’hai gavna*, every answer he got was a
similar type of answer. לבסוף *L’basar*, the last בית כנסת *beis knesses*,
אמר ליה פסוק לי פסוקך *amar lei pesok li pesukach*, he said
to the child, "Tell me your פסוק *pasuk*." אמר לו *Amar lo*,
ולרשע אמר אלהים מה לך לספר חוקי *ve’l’rasha amar Elokim mah lecha
l’saper chukai*, "And to the wicked one says God, what are you
doing talking about My, you know, My edicts?" So being basically means
you have no business even not only can you not do תשובה
*teshuvah*, but you should not even be talking תורה *Torah*. If you
are a רשע *rasha*, what business do you have talking תורה *Torah*?
ההוא ינוקא *Hahu yanuka*, now that child, הוה מגמגם בלישניה *havah megamgem
b’lishneih*, had a little problem enunciating. אשתמע *Ishtama*, and it sounded כמאן
דאמר ליה *k’man d’amar lei*, it sounded like he was saying to
him not ולרשע אמר אלהים *u’l’rasha amar Elokim* but ולאלישע אמר אלהים
*u’l’Elisha amar Elokim*. Like, to אלישע *Elisha* God is saying, "What are
you doing talking, you know, talking תורה *Torah*?" איכא דאמרי *Ika d’amri*,
so some say, סכינא הוה בהדיה *sakina havah bahadeih*, that he אלישע
*Elisha* had a knife in his hand with him, וקרעיה *ve’karei*, and
he he dismembered this child. This is a real פילגש בגבעה *Pilegesh
b’Givah* type of a story. ושדריה לתליסר בי כנישתא *ve’shadrei l’tlasar bei
knishta*, and he sent the the pieces out to the other thirteen
shuls that had given him the bad answers. Okay, it's really like
the פילגש בגבעה *Pilegesh b’Givah*, cutting it up and sending to all
the. Anyway, ואיכא דאמרי *ve’ika d’amri*, some say, אמר *amar*, he said,
אי הוה בידי סכינא *ei havah biyadi sakina*, if I had a
knife in my hand, הוה קרענא ליה *havah karina lei*, I would
have dismembered him. But so by the way part of this idea
is like that's shock. Right? I bet nobody in their life of
hearing stories of אלישע בן אבויה probably has heard the story that
אלישע בן אבויה chopped up this little kid and dismembered him. Okay,
that's not normally how we associate it. Heresy is leaving the religious
faith and so on. But it makes it easier also to deal
with how he's been rejected, right? 'Cause and we're going to see
later in the גמרא that there's a certain sympathy towards him. He
was such a youth not just the רבי מאיר story that רבי
מאיר was ready to learn from him, but like trying to save
him from the דין din of גיהנום. Gehennom. He was such a
huge תלמיד חכם, talmid chacham, his sin it was basically an intellectual
one. So here, by making him a murderer, it's sort of helpful
for if you want to make it easier on yourself to understand
how he has been completely sort of put on the outs and
rejected. Look how far away. If it didn't start there, that's at
least where it ends. At least in this. But this is again
a later addition to those earlier stories. One minute, כי נח נפשיה
דאחר. ki nach nafshieh d'Acher. Now here's the story about that ambivalence.
When אחר died, אמרי לא מדיינין ליה דייני. amri lo m'dainin lei
daini. Again, this is all later גמרא versions of the story, it's
all in Aramaic. They said up in heaven, he should not be
judged, he should not be punished, ולא לעלמא דאתי לא אתי v'lo
l'olma d'atei lo atei but he also shouldn't come to the עולם
הבא. Olam Ha-Ba. לא מדיינין ליה דייני lo m'dainin lei daini he
should not be judged משום דעסק באורייתא. mishum d'asak b'Oraita. He learned
תורה and he achieved great levels in תורה. ולא לעלמא דאתי לא
אתי v'lo l'olma d'atei lo atei but he can't get עולם הבא
Olam Ha-Ba משום דחטא. mishum d'chata. אמר רבי מאיר, Amar Rabbi Meir,
so רבי מאיר, his student said, מוטב דלידייניה וליתי לעלמא דאתי, mutav
d'lidainei v'lyatei l'olma d'atei, it would be better that he should be
judged for his sins and then he could get עולם הבא Olam
Ha-Ba afterwards. At least give him the, at least he'll suffer but
he'll get then his ultimate reward. So מתי אמות, matai amus, when
will I die, said רבי מאיר, ואעלה עשן מקברו v'a'aleh ashan mikivro
and I'll go up to basically argue his case up in heaven
and I will cause that smoke will come out of his grave.
Now that doesn't sound like a good thing, but it means it'll
just be symbolic of his judgment in גיהנום, Gehennom but if it's,
it'll be good that he'll be judged in גיהנום, Gehennom, then he'll
be able to get עולם הבא. Olam Ha-Ba. כי נח נפשיה דרבי
מאיר, ki nach nafshieh d'Rabbi Meir, and when רבי מאיר did pass
away, סליק קוטרא מקבריה דאחר, salik kutra mikivrieh d'Acher, so lo and
behold, smoke came up from the grave of אחר. אמר רבי יוחנן,
Amar Rabbi Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan said, גבורה למקלי רביה? gevurah
l'mikli rabieh? What, is it a big thing in order to cause
your רבי to burn? So he did not feel this was a
good solution to the problem that רבי מאיר was getting אחר burnt
in גיהנום. Gehennom So חד הוה ביננא chad havei beinana or when
one was among us ולא מצינן לאצוליה, v'lo matzinan l'atzulei,
and we couldn't save him when he was among us. Right? This
is also sort of the sad irony of the story. Now after
he's dead, we're going to save him. When רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan
is saying when he was here and he was alive, we weren't
able to do anything for him.
אי נקטיה ביד מאן מרמי ליה מאן. ee nakteih b'yad man marmi
leih man. If I would,
if I would grab on to him with my hand, somebody would
take him from me. Meaning he's saying I would do, if I
would do it, I would make sure that he would get up
to גן עדן, Gan Eden. I wouldn't just cause him to be
judged in גיהנום. Gehennom So if I would hold on to his
hand, he'd be taken from me. אמר, and therefore רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan said, מתי אמות שאכבה עשן מקברו. matai amus she'achbeh ashan mikivro.
When will I die and I'll cause the smoke to cease from
his grave. כי נח נפשיה דרבי יוחנן, ki nach nafshieh d'Rabbi Yochanan,
and when רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan died, פסק קוטרא מקבריה דאחר, pasak
kutra mikivrieh d'Acher, the smoke ceased from the grave of אחר. פתח
עליה ההוא ספדנא, patach aleih hahu safdana, that goes back to my
Katten, the eulogizer opened up on him, אפילו שומר הפתח לא עמד
לפניך רבנו. afilu shomer hapetach lo amad l'fanecha rabbeinu.
Even the guardian of the gate of גיהנום could not stand against
רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan managed to get through
the guardian of the gate of גיהנום, find אחר, grab onto his
hand and שלעפ schlep him up to
גן עדן. So this is quite fascinating, right? Because I bet also
this is not a מדרש that you have heard, that actually רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan managed to get אחר into גן עדן, because that's
equally troubling. What? He was this big heretic and got into גן
עדן? You have these two very different types of stories one right
against the other which are dealing with this real ambivalence around אחר.
And I should just point out going forward about a thousand years
or a thousand years that post-שבתי צבי, Shabbetai Tzvi, you find people
that were even not the
Sabbatians but were sort of like, somehow still impressed by his powers
and whatever, that even like a hundred years after the שבתי צבי
Shabbetai Tzvi had died, stories also about him like being saved from
גיהנום and who's going to redeem his soul from גיהנום and bring
it up to גן עדן. So similar types of like ambivalences around
the, recognizing how terrible it was what the person did, but also
appreciating this person's like spiritual greatness. Yes. Most heretics of that time
did everything they could to get Jews to go off the דרך.
Right? אחר is trying to protect רבי מאיר. That's a good point,
that's a good point, so to acknowledge the credit he gets there
of just saying let me do my stuff but not wanting to
sort of influence others. Okay, more about אחר tomorrow. I'll leave you
with a cliffhanger. All right.